<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The poor man's mite, unto the more large contributions of the liberal, at this day freely added, in testimony of that respect which is born unto the faithful and their interest, as it's laid up and hid in Jesus. Briefly discovering, 1. The vanity of that rejoycing, which seems to glory in any thing save the Lord. 2. What is required of all that expect to have the form of the Lords house revealed unto them. 3. That however the chief corner-stone may be rejected, none other foundation can no man lay. 4. That as Christ shall appear, so with him shall the interest of the second of new creation, appear with him in glory. 5. A postscript, or additional word to the reader, occasioned by the late revived noise of uniformity, or national conformity to the principles of some men.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1659</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 28 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A90835</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P2867</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E986_3</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R207764</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99866796</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99866796</idno>
            <idno type="VID">119082</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A90835)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 119082)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 147:E986[3])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The poor man's mite, unto the more large contributions of the liberal, at this day freely added, in testimony of that respect which is born unto the faithful and their interest, as it's laid up and hid in Jesus. Briefly discovering, 1. The vanity of that rejoycing, which seems to glory in any thing save the Lord. 2. What is required of all that expect to have the form of the Lords house revealed unto them. 3. That however the chief corner-stone may be rejected, none other foundation can no man lay. 4. That as Christ shall appear, so with him shall the interest of the second of new creation, appear with him in glory. 5. A postscript, or additional word to the reader, occasioned by the late revived noise of uniformity, or national conformity to the principles of some men.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 13, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for Livewell Chapman, at the Crown in Popes-Head-Alley,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1659.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "June. 13.".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Second Advent --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Faith --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:119082:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE POOR MAN'S <hi>MITE, Unto the more large CONTRIBUTIONS of the LIBERAL, At this day freely added, in Teſtimony of that reſpect which is born unto the faithful and their intereſt, as it's laid up and hid in Jeſus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>BRIEFLY DISCOVERING,</hi>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>1.</hi> The vanity of that rejoycing, which ſeems to glory in any thing ſave the Lord.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>2.</hi> What is required of all that expect to have the form of the Lords houſe revealed unto them.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>3.</hi> That however the chief Corner-ſtone may be rejected, none other foundation can no man lay.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>4.</hi> That as Chriſt ſhall appear, ſo with him ſhall the intereſt of the ſecond or new Creation, appear with him in glory.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>5.</hi> A Poſtſcript, or Additional word to the Reader, occaſioned by the a late revived noiſe of Uniformity, or national Conformity to the principles of ſome men.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>London, <hi>Printed for</hi> Livewell Chapman, <hi>at the Crown in Popes-Head-Alley. 1659.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:119082:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:119082:2"/>
            <head>THE POOR MAN'S <hi>MITE.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>SINCE the late wonderful appearance of wiſdome and power from on high, bringing down the haughty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of inſulting arrogant fleſh; preſenting to view the ſecret devouring Contrivances of the old enemy, which under a new name and pretence of doing the good former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly left undone, the more covertly intended the accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the things they would have done. So many have been the valuable and worthy Teſtimonies of the faithful that are gone before me, That at this time my ſelf, of all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, had leaſt encouragement to contribute my mite. And were it not that a more then ordinary ſence of the vanity that may be written upon man, (as man) in his very beſt Eſtate, and of the unwearied endeavours of the great ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſary of Light and Truth, to obſtruct its dawnings and breakings forth upon the Children of men, is ſtir'd up in my heart; I ſhould have been altogether ſilent: but for that from both theſe, to wit, the vanity of man, and the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued diſpight of the enemy, no leſs then occaſions of Godly jealouſy, if not of fears and doubts, is adminiſtred to both the youthy and the more aged Chriſtian (though I confeſs the ſame, with exceeding wearineſs of minde and meekneſs of ſpirit, ought to have its entertainment, even in the very thoughts of a man) I am as one in ſome degree awakened, and made willing, in tenderneſs and faithfulneſs
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:119082:3"/>
of heart at this time, to offer a few things to the ſerious conſideration of the faithful, with whom though I ſeek not for what may gratify a carnal intereſt, cannot but hope to finde at leaſt a tincture of that heavenly Spirit of love, which rather helps to improve, then reject the ſmalleſt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance of true love and reſpect to them, and their ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting concerns, though it proceed from one of the meaneſt of all their Fathers family.</p>
            <p>The firſt thing offered is, That of God is Chriſt made unto his people Wiſdome, Righteouſneſs, Sanctification, and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption, to the end that if any would glory, they ſhould glory in the Lord.</p>
            <p>The infinite Father of Wiſdom, Grace, whoſe name is the Lord, and will not give his glory to another, foreſeeing the evil that would be ſpringing up in the heart of man, to the cauſing of him to turn aſide, and depart from the living God, by an Eſſay to become Wiſdome, Righteouſneſs, Sanctifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Redemption to its ſelf, was therefore pleaſed in much wiſdome,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prov.</hi> 8.</note> to place the Fountain of all durable Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, Riches and Righteouſneſs in his Son, as a life occult or hid with him, to whom the name of a Redeemer belongs, in whoſe preſence every knee ſhall bow, or ſmite together, and every tongue confeſs to God, that this is He in whom all fulneſs dwells.</p>
            <p>From whence proceeds a loud voyce of admonition and caution unto all the Children of men, to be careful, leſt at any time they ſhould be tempted to depart from the Fountain of living waters, and hew out to themſelves Ciſterns, yea broken Ciſterns, that can hold no water; which two are evils commonly committed at once: for no ſooner do men begin to hew out Ciſterns to themſelves, but at the ſame time they are found departing from the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Spring and Fountain of Life; but who are found in the practiſe thereof, ſeldome eſcape the evil of their doings: know therefore and ſee, O all ye inhabitans of this Iſle, That it is an evil thing and a bitter to forſake the Lord.</p>
            <p>For the evil of our own diſtruſtful imaginations will co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:119082:3"/>
us, &amp; our backſlidings ſhall reprove us: for what hath the Redeemed to do in the way of <hi>Egypt</hi> or <hi>Aſſyria,</hi> or with the waters of <hi>Shihor,</hi> to drink in the ſhallow &amp; corrupted ſtreams thereof? Is not the Fountain opened, whereunto all that thirſt may come, and he that hath no mony nor price, may come and receive freely of that fullneſs, which is to make him fruitful in a dry Land?</p>
            <p>But Poor man having loſt his firſt image, wherein he was created, as in a poſture meet to receive a more laſting and durable comelyneſs from God, had he with patience waited for the bringing forth thereof (though he be not Ignorant of his preſent depravity, and from whence he is fallen) yet ſuch is the pride of his heart, that finding no price in himſelf, that will render him acceptable, rather chuſeth to truſt to and live upon the petty waterings of ſome borrowed ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhment, then give the leaſt reception to the water of Life, becauſe it's freely offered: which ingrateful and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicious principle opens the largeſt door of entrance into the heart of man, for the grand oppoſer of grace and truth, as it came by Jeſus Chriſt, that is imaginable; and is to be la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented, as one of the foreſt evils that can happen to a Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or People, that in the day of their viſitation have not hearts to underſtand, nor wills to receive or affect the things that concern their peace: and I could be glad that even this were leſs the ſin of this Nation, then the many broken Ciſterns of late hewed out and found in it ſeems to declare: wherefore it highly concerns us, even now ere it be too late, whileſt we are upon the wheele, to ceaſe from man whoſe breath is in his noſtrils, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fainedly to return from the evil of our former wayes, and to make our wayes and our doings good, leſt by our further abuſe of the grace and patience of God, we at laſt become as veſſels utterly moved, or as <hi>Jeremies</hi> Bottle, that having paſt the tryal of both wheele and furnace, being then bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, cannot be made whole again.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That, if <hi>Iſrael</hi> ſhall be aſhamed of, and return from their iniquities, the Lord will ſhew them the form of his
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:119082:4"/>
houſe, for his Arme is not ſhortned that it cannot ſave, but our ſins ſeparate betwixt our God and us: And if after a ſtrict enquiry made for the ſin of <hi>Iſrael:</hi> in the day when the Lord alone had been their wiſdome and ſtrength, it be found that the thoughts we had of our ſelves or others (who were but inſtruments, not the cauſe of our delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rances) beyond what ought to have been thought, are none of the ſmalleſt of our offences, how ought all the Lords people, though of different judgments and perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, to be one, even in a lamenting this, and all other our evills committed againſt the Lord, that yet ſpareth us, as a man ſpareth his ſon that ſerveth him, and to be provoking one another to walk anſwerable to the wonderful mercies conferred upon us, leaſt the Lords returning to viſit us with favour amongſt men be miſ improved, and by agrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting our former diſobedience, impatience, and ingratitude, a worſe thing happen unto us?</p>
            <p>And now ye honourable ones whom the Lord (we hope in mercy to your ſelves and us) hath reſtored to your former ſtation or places of truſt; Though it be Judged that you have not wanted remembrances on the Lords be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half at this day, yet its alſo hoped that it will not be an offence to you (eſpecially the truly meekned and humbled ones among you) to hear, though from a babe, that if with full purpoſe of heart ye reſolve to decline the evills of the Times paſt, when men acted partly for God and partly for themſelves, and become intire and true to the intereſt of God and the faithful; that with him it is to ſhew you the form of his houſe, who will not only be found amongſt you in ſo doing, but in the day when he ſhall come to make up his Jewels, and to enquire for what honour hath been done to <hi>Mordecai</hi> for his fidelity to the King of Kings, he will crown you as wiſe Maſter-builders; and even now whileſt ye are a building, if ye keep cloſe to him in your undertakings, will enable you to carry on his work againſt all the <hi>Tobias's,</hi> and <hi>Sanballats</hi> of this age, who doubtleſs by aſmuch as in them lyes, will endeavour the hindring
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:119082:4"/>
and impeding thereof: for they love not the proſperity of <hi>Zion,</hi> and every appearance of the new <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> is an offence to them. And ſome of them have been made to own the Lord and his people amongſt men (yea wicked men) who ſaving their vizards were ravening Wolves and greedy Lions, that gaped for the time, when the innocent ſhould become their prey. But for ever magnified be that name, whoſe mercy is above all his works; <hi>Daniel</hi> is eſcaped, and ye are owned in the day of the Lords appearing, thus far to viſit and redeem his people: Wherefore be it ever remembred as pertinent and beſuiting us, That when the breaches began to be ſtopped, and the walls of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> were built; the builders and people were much caſt down in their own eyes, for they perceived that the work was wrought of God, at every of whoſe appearing to work, let the fearful and unbelieving learn to become obedient, and comply with the pure intereſt of God and his people, in all the degrees, ariſings and gradations thereof: for you will finde its of force enough to work out it ſelf through all the heaps of thick darkneſs, which the Prince of the Aire and Children of diſobedience hath this many hundred of years been caſting upon it, and will ſurely ſhelter, and all the day long be a covering to thoſe that love and cheriſh it.</p>
            <p>And who ſo ſoares in this Region, are in Communion and correſpondency with the ſpiritual and hidden opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of this Intereſt; To ſuch no greater folly is there, nor more apparent, then the ſpouſing or contracting there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto the intereſt of the fleſh, or wordly power and wiſdom, (as the needful expedient) to haſten the work of God among men, by joyning together what God would have put aſunder: which attempts henceforward as Light and Truth riſeth higher in the Earth, may ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect by the wiſe in heart, to be eſteemed and accounted of, for none other then the fruit of a carnal, ſelfiſh, degene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rating principle, that will at laſt evidently demonſtrate the Attempters to be Children in whom there is no faith, and after a large pretence to ſerve none other King but Jeſus,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:119082:5"/>
give the World an occaſion to ſay, Lo, this is the man that made not God his ſtrength.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 5.</note> When <hi>Ephraim</hi> ſaw his wound, and <hi>Judah</hi> his ſickneſs, they ſent to the <hi>Aſſyrian,</hi> and to King <hi>Jareb,</hi> but they could not heal them.</p>
            <p>And therefore ye worthy builders, whoſe experience hath out-lived the riſe and fall of much of this kinde of do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings in <hi>England,</hi> the hopes of the faithful enlightned ones are, that your wiſdoms will be ſuch, as to make a righteous advantage thereof to redeem the time paſt, for the dayes were, (and are) very evil: and how little the laſt five or ſix years added to the ſetting up of any thing that's able (or ought) to ſtand, notwithſtanding the ſpecious pretences made thereunto, I leave to all that are concerned to judge, who after a general ſurvey of things, I fear will hardly finde any thing lifted up that's more abiding (or deſerve to be ſo) then an Image of wax, that's either capable of receiving another Impreſſion, or in a ſhort time lyable to be thrown to the ground.</p>
            <p>Honoured Sirs, though our purpoſe is not to be tedious, yet foraſmuch as the concerns of a worldly political Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt leaves you not unpreſented with ſeeming plauſible and ſubſtantial bottomes to work upon, (to the intent the chief Corner-ſtone may be rejected or laid aſide) it may not therefore be omitted to reminde here, That none other foundation can no man lay, and proſper, then that which is laid, which is Jeſus Chriſt: and if any as wiſe Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter workmen ſhall build thereon, their works will be tryed, and the durable ſubſtance thereof revealed, and that by fire; and accordingly ſhall the reward of every builder be: for by how much the work will not abide the tryal, by ſo much ſhall the loſs of the workman be: wherefore in all your undertakings to build, be ſure to digg deep till you meet with the Rock of ages for your foundations; Then you will not need to fear, though ſtormes ariſe, the winde blow, the rain deſcend, or though <hi>Aſhdod, Ammon</hi> &amp; <hi>Moab</hi> be offend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed or inraged, for the proſperity of the Lords work: for the Lord himſelf hath reſpect unto it, and by his own everlaſting
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:119082:5"/>
arm ſhall every true <hi>Nehemia</hi> be preſerved and born up.</p>
            <p>The laſt things offered to the faithful in general, are, that when Chriſt who is our Life ſhall appear, we alſo ſhall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear with him in glory: now we are ſons; but it doth not appear what we ſhall be: but we know that when he doth appear, we ſhall be like him, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>As hereby the purpoſe of the Lords Servants may be underſtood to work out from amongſt the Saints the evil of an unbelieving heart, if by all means poſſible they might beget in them a lively hope, or an ability to hope to the end; ſo they ſeem to promiſe the ſafety of a believers intereſt, as it's rooted and laid upon a Rock that's higher then they: the which whoſoever is made truly to believe, and ſee as with the eye of faith, maketh not haſt, but is ready to wait for its further comings down upon him, or untill the Lord ſhall ſay, Come up hither; and having been as it were, in a mount, where a more ample and certain view of their Life and intereſt is given them, they ceaſe not to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove the exerciſe of faith, as well when they are comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to deſcend as when to aſcend; knowing he to whom they have committed themſelves, is God of the valleys as as well as of the hills.</p>
            <p>And for our advantage herein, if the firſt man <hi>Adam</hi> a living ſoul, and the ſecond as the quickning Spirit or Lord from Heaven, be but conſidered as the two principles or Rocks from whence proceeds, (to be diſcerned) the nature of both Creations, the one as earthly in its beſt ſtrength and beauty, the other as heavenly, the ſame yeſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day, and to day, and for ever; it gives a certain kinde of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration of things carnal or things Spiritual, in their ſeveral attainments.</p>
            <p>The firſt <hi>Adam</hi> was the root of the firſt or fleſhly Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and in him the ſun of its glory was found as Light ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered up into the body of the Sun; and being created as is ſaid, In the Image of God, typified or prefigured the Son of God, that was to be revealed as head unto both; and whileſt in its eſtate of ſimplicity, <hi>Adam</hi> continued living in
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:119082:6"/>
Communion with God, walking in the enjoyment and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticipation of a Life, which had its ſole dependance upon him: he was in ſhort a glorious piece, the map or abridg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of things created both in Heaven and in Earth.</p>
            <p>But all this glory and excellency, through the temptation of the Devil, (and the help created) for <hi>Adam,</hi> and the weakneſs or mutability of that Eſtate in its own nature, leaves God, and is drawn away to ſeek after a life in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in diſtinction from that everlaſting Life, Wiſdome, and Righteouſneſs, which God would have been unto it, in the day of his ſecond or next appearance to <hi>Adam.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecond <hi>Adam,</hi> the Lord from Heaven, is the Root of all the new Creation, which is Created according to God, in righteouſneſs; in reſpect of which eſtate, as proceeding from the ancient of dayes, and being Rooted and principled in him, the moſt glorious and higheſt attainment of the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer is in the ſpiritual mans account, or him that judgeth all things, but earthy and fading.</p>
            <p>A ſerious contemplation of both theſe, or of the day which <hi>Abraham</hi> ſaw afar off and was glad, a proſpect is opened into the ſecond or new Creations intereſt, as it is laid up and ſecured in its Root, and will according to every ſeaſon proper to its appearance, be breaking forth in the ſeveral degrees and parts thereof, working myſteriouſly and effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctually through all the devices of Satan, and the wiſdome of fleſh, which as a grand competitor conſtant to it ſelf in all things, is very ready to challenge the name or birth-right, of a created help, that by no mean may be rejected or turn'd off the ſtage; and notwithſtanding the right it pleads to co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partnerſhip with the wiſdom of God, or the ſimplicity, that is in Jeſus, ſhall at laſt be ſentenced for ever to depart, as the fruit of, and proceeding from an adulterous act committed between the Sons of God &amp; the Daughters of men, and not judged worthy to ſhare the in bleſſed fruit of the faith and patience of the true ſeed; who being wrought to up to ſee where, and with whom their life and intereſt is as a naile faſtned in a ſure place, become ſtedfaſt and unmoveable in
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:119082:6"/>
their hopes, and of an ability to draw out or extract ſome good from every appearance of evil; and whileſt the adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary preys upon their Bodies, they rejoyce in their Head, the firſt, and the laſt, the root and the off-ſpring of <hi>David,</hi> the bright morning-Star, and to his people the day-ſpring from on high, whileſt the Enemies cruelty bring thick dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs upon themſelves.</p>
            <p>So that in the day the Enemies of the Jews hoped to have power over them, it was turned to the contrary,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſth.</hi> 9.11.</note> and the Jews had rule over them that hated them.</p>
            <p>Thus to ſee the Lord in times of the greateſt unlikely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, ſo eminently to make known his ſalvation to his people, when the Rulers of the Earth conſpire, and take Counſel together againſt them; how ſhould it work us off from ſeeking to hide our intereſt, our life in any thing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low himſelf, who is able to make all things to work toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for good to thoſe that love and fear him; but notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the wonderful occaſions that have been given to believe this, a Spirit too much the contrary hath appeared, even many that once ſeemed to have clean eſcaped the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluences of lo here, or lo there; So that with them, what was <hi>Paul, Apollos,</hi> or <hi>Cephas?</hi> is not Chriſt the Head? or is there any other King but Jeſus? and yet after all this, as opportunity is preſented, either in private or publique con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns, are joyning iſſue with <hi>Aſhdod, Ammon</hi> and <hi>Moah;</hi> ſo that when the work of the Lord was to be promoted, the language of a true Iſraelite would not be underſtood in our Land, and no man cared to hear any other then the lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage of his own people, or that whereunto he had eſpou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed himſelf; and that amongſt the reſt is feared to be an evil of no mean dye, and calls for more then an overly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance from all that have been joyning hands therewith, leſt the Lord be provoked ſuddenly to appear terribly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the whole off-ſpring and proceed of that adulterous conjunction.</p>
            <p>And now ye remnant of the little flock, that are riſen with Chriſt, minde the things that are above; lay up trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:119082:7"/>
where neither moth not ruſt doth corrupt: for if your inclinations be earthly, ſo will your expectations be: as the Lord hath not been wanting to you, be you therefore ready to anſwer the abundant favour beſtowed upon you. The de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices of Satan are many, to chill your affection &amp; to harden your hearts one againſt another; be wiſe therefore in your day, be not inſnared, let brotherly love continue; and let not parts nor gifts create diſſentions amongſt you, or cauſe you to juſtle in the broad way. If ye have received, be thankful: remember that God is love; and he that dwelleth in him, dwelleth in love, it is the fulfilling of the Law, the more excellent way, wherein (notwithſtanding the endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours of the Enemy to the contrary) my hopes are to ſee you walk readily and chearfully without offences, or giving any occaſion to judge you in meats or drinks, or in reſpect of an holy day: And that there will be given a Spirit of wiſdome, of ſound Judgment, and true diſcerning to the upright in heart, to make great uſe of the preſent diverſities of Spirits, that ſeem to be in ſwift motion at this day to propagate the intereſt of God, and to cheriſh the power of true godlineſs, whereſoever and in whomſoever it ſhall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear: for as Chriſt appears more and more, ſo ſhall his Image of true Godlineſs appear in his people, more eaſy to be diſcerned; and not only the Righteouſneſs of the Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous ſhall be diſcovered, but alſo the hypocriſie of the hypocrite: for as the glory of Iſrael ſhall break out, ſo will the nakedneſs of <hi>Edom</hi> or <hi>Eſau</hi> be made bare. Until the far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther accompliſhment whereof, Oh that we may all in a right Spirit, reſt in the Lord, and ſtay our ſelves upon our God, waiting patiently for him, whoſe coming will be in Judgment to his enemies, and in favour to all that love his appearing.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:119082:7"/>
            <head>Poſt-ſcript.</head>
            <p>SInce the late wanted noiſe of Uniformity, or national uniformity to the principles of ſome men, hath been revived in our Ears, It remembred me, that when the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple were all of one language, it's ſaid they travel'd together, until they came into the Land of <hi>Shinar,</hi> where (as may be judged) they found a pleaſant plain, and meeting with a place ſo goodly for habitation, ſaid one unto another, Come let's make brick, and burn them throughly, that we may build us a City or a Tower, and leave us a name, &amp;c. Now when by many of this Nation, the ſeveral Hills that were riſen in it, had been paſſed over, and in their travel the great Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal Mountain trampled under and levelled with the ground, they judg'd the place wherunto they were then come would prove a plain of great fruitfulneſs, and that the tenths there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of would be of great value, therefore coveted to make it the place of their continual abode, and cared not to follow the Lord any farther; but ſpeedily ſought how to eſtabliſh and ſettle themſelves in that ſtate whereunto they had attained, ſo as never to advance one jot towards the Price of a higher calling, though it were even ſaid unto them, Ariſe, depart, that is not your reſt; but rather haſtned to erect ſome monſtrous Tower or great <hi>Babel</hi> for their defence: and that contrivance being blaſted by a voyce of noyſe and confuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on from on high, cauſing the people to ſcatter abroad, and run to and fro, through which knowledge is increaſed in the Earth, the artificers rage, and are diſquieted, for that their good old Cauſe (as they call it) is not like to proſper: And know not how enough to vent themſelves, (but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membring, that from the Nobility to the ribaldry of <hi>England</hi> Popery hath been, and ſtill is by moſt abominated, as helliſh and <hi>Diabolical,</hi> and the rather amongſt all, for that they have been ſo full of bloody, cruel and murtherous plots and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:119082:8"/>
that would at any time have eſtabliſhed it, as our Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions Religion,) betake them to a publick upbraiding and charging of others, with what themſelves are moſt guilty of, <hi>viz.</hi> the opening a door of entrance for the Pope and his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion in <hi>England.</hi> I wiſh the Hierarchy and other the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogant uſurpations of that Antichriſtian Biſhop, were leſs cheriſhed and upheld in the practice of thoſe men, who would have all men to be of their minds, but not to be as they are, Teachers of the people, or Maſters in <hi>Iſrael:</hi> but the dayes haſten, when the Lord ſhall be known to be the Teacher of his people, and many that call themſelves Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters now, do it becauſe they would be Maſters, pretend to Chriſt, and ſet up the Cuſtome of the Jews, and by their tradition violate the ſimplicity of the Goſpel, lay claim to the maintenance of that Prieſt-hood, whoſe order and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing they are called (as they ſay) to preach down; and yet are no Prieſts, but Miniſters; I think ſo indeed, and whoſe they are, and whom they ſerve, every day more then other ſeems to manifeſt. Now to the ingenuous Reader I leave it to judge, which are more like to gratify the intereſt of <hi>Rome,</hi> or become her falſe Biſhops agent, theſe men who with their national Uniformity would compaſs Sea and Land to gaine proſelytes; or people deſirous to be found according to the Word of God, in a Goſpel-ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion from the corrupted and beaſtly generations of the Earth, that will not learn Righteouſneſs, though they faint in Judgment: and for a further diſcovery of this principle (as it hath been offered) I refer the Reader to Mr. <hi>Deales</hi> diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe thereon, called Uniformity examined; and wiſh they may henceforward better improve the gifts and parts, and learning they boaſt ſo much of, to a better uſe, then to li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit the Holy one of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> who knows how to call a Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſherman, and reject a Rabbi; or ſo much to ſet themſelves to throw down all others, as if they were the only ones, and wiſdome muſt dye with them: but who are ſo blinde as a people that will not ſee; or deaf, as thoſe that will not hear? What the effect of their deſpiſing the day of ſmall things may
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:119082:8"/>
be, is rather feared then determined: and who knows but in the day when it moſt concerns them, having eyes they ſhal not ſee, and having ears they ſhall not hear? this Judgment is not wiſhed unto them, but rather hearts to follow one of their Eminent friends, in truth (not in hypocriſie) to confeſs, that now they are made to know there is a God in Heaven: whoſe ſo doing, ſome of their greateſt Rabbies once ſaid in my hearing, would prove worſe then a thouſand worſters to them; So that it may be that the ſeeming private peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of a Champion of theirs, will be worth the having in publique, whether it be done by the Confeſſor in truth or no.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
